George, Manfred; Papers ger038
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Manfred George Papers
1913-1968
Undated
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ger038
2.87 cubic ft.
This collection contains photocopies of correspondence written by Manfred George to various public figures, original manuscripts of plays composed by George, newspaper clippings of articles George wrote for European and American publications, and audio recordings on his work with the New York based newspaper Aufbau.
Biographical Sketch
Born in Berlin in 1893, Manfred George became an established theater critic in Germany during the interwar period. An outspoken leftist, George fled Germany after the Nazi Party gained control of the government in 1933. After travelling to a number of European countries and writing for various newspapers, George eventually settled in the United States, where he became editor-in-chief of the German-language newspaper Aufbau - a position he held from 1939 to his death in 1965. In this role, George saw the paper develop from a small monthly newsletter with limited readership into a leading outlet for the voices of the burgeoning German-speaking Jewish community in America. Due to his position with the organization, George became a central figure in the German émigré anti-Nazi movement in America.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains copies of correspondence with Hannah Arendt, Max Barth, Hans Habe, Thomas Mann, Ludwig Marcuse, Hertha Pauli, and many other émigré scholars and writers (1933–1968); two reel-to-reel tape recordings concerning the New York émigré newspaper Aufbau; copies of press clippings of articles by Manfred George in European and American newspapers (1913–1955); a number of original manuscripts written by Manfred George (1920-1938); and materials pertaining to the German-American Writers' Association (1938–1940).
Arrangement
The collection is organized alphabetically. There are no series.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
All items in this collection were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives. This manuscript group was photocopied by the University Libraries in part from scrapbooks at Aufbau offices and in part from George's papers with the permission of George's widow before the originals were sent to the Deutsches Literaturarchiv (German Literature Archive), Marbach am Neckar, Germany.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Correspondence; Germany--Emigration and immigration
- 25th Jahre Aufbau (side 2), Undated (Reel 1)
- 30th Anniversary - New World Club, Hunter College, Undated (Reel 2)
- About Aufbau, 1942-1945; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Arendt, Hannah, 1947-1948; 1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Articles Concerning the Theater, Theater Criticism, 1921-1930; 1932; Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Articles on Various Personalities, 1916-1917; 1920; 1923-1933; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Aufbau, 1948 January-1948 June (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Aufbau, 1948 July-1948 December (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Aufbau, 1949 January-1949 July (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Aufbau, 1949 August-1949 December (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Aufbau, 1950 January-1950 April (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Aufbau, 1950 May-1950 August (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Aufbau, 1950 September-1950 December (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Aufbau, 1951 January-1951 April (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Aufbau, 1951 May-1951 September (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Aufbau, 1951 October-1951 December (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Aufbau, 1952 January-1952 April (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Aufbau, 1952 May-1952 September (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Aufbau, 1955 May (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Aufhäuser, Siegfried, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- "Aufruhr im Warenhaus", Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Aviad, Yakov, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Barth, Max, 1942; 1965; 1968 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Becher, Johannes R., 1939 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Book Reviews, 1913; 1915-1916; 1919-1922; 1924-1932; Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Carow, Erich, Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Daniel, Anita, 1947-1948; 1950-1954; Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- "Die Ewige Braut", Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Dieterle, William and Charlotte, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- "Der Fall Gödeberg", Undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
- "Der Führer", 1920 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- "Der Kamerad Oedon von Horvath", 1938 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- "Der Hut in Deutschen Dichtung", 1951 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- "Der Rote Ring", Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
- "Der Weg des Glaubens", Undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
- "Die Geburts des Incubus", Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- "Die Große Nachtricht", Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- "Die Heilige von Oesterbotten", Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- "Die Hexe von Oesterbotten", Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- "Die Nummer Läuft", 1925; Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- "Die Verhexte Schenke", Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Editions du Carrefour, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- "Ein Abend in der Hölle", Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- "Ein Dichter des Volkes", Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- "Ein Freund der Menschheit", Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- "Ein Gefährliches Interview", Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- "Ein Hut und Ein Mantel", Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- "Ein Stück aus dem Tollhaus", 1931 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- "Eines Nachts in Kattowitz", Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Feuchtwanger, Marta, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Feuilletons Essays, 1916-1917; 1919; 1921-1929; Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Ficker, Ludwig, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Film Reviews (1 of 2), 1916-1919; 1921-1938; 1946-1947; Undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Film Reviews (2 of 2), 1916-1919; 1921-1938; 1946-1947; Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
- "Gabriela", Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
- German-American Writers Association, 1938; Undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
- German-American Writers Association, 1939; Undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
- German-American Writers Association, 1940; Undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
- General Correspondence, 1937; 1965 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- "Grabbes Doppeltes Gesicht", Undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Graf, Oskar Maria, 1939-1940; 1962-1963; Undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Habe, Hans, 1943; 1964-1965; Undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
- "Heimkehr", Undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Herzog, Wilhelm, 1943; 1945; 1952 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Hiller, Kurt, 1940-1941; 1945; 1947; 1954 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Hochwälder, Fritz, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Horkheimer, Max, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- "Hünchen", Undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Javits, Senator Jacob, 1947-1956; 1963; Undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Judische Revue, 1936-1938; Undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Kaleko, Mascha, 1945; 1947 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Kalenter, Ossip, 1935-1937; 1939-1940; 1945-1952; 1955; 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Kasack, Hermann, 1945; 1947; Undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Kauder, Gustav, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Kayser, Rudolf, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Kersten, Kurt (1 of 2), 1936-1947; 1951; 1953-1957; 1960; Undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Kersten, Kurt (2 of 2), 1936-1947; 1951; 1953-1957; 1960; Undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Kesser, Hermann, 1933; 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Kesten, Hermann, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Kohner, Frederick, 1934; 1936; 1940 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Kohner, Paul, 1940; Undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
- "La Paule", Undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Lustig, Hans and Lotte, 1934; 1964; Undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
- M. George: JFK Obituary Speech, 1964 November 22; 1966 January (Reel 2)
- "Madame Tussaud", Undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Mann, Erika, 1934; 1940; 1953; Undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Mann, Thomas, 1943; 1945; 1951-1952; 1954 (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Marcus, Paul Erich, 1947; 1959; Undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Marcuse, Ludwig, 1933-1937; Undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
- "Moni und die Herbstlichen", 1930 (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Mundt, H.J., 1949 (Box 2, Folder 55)
- Neue Zeitung, 1948-1951; Undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
- Neue Zeitung, 1952-1954; Undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
- "No Man's Land", Undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
- Nürnberg, Rolf, 1934-1936; 1940; 1947-1948; Undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
- Ouerborl, Danny and Joe, Undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
- Pariser Tageblatt, 1934-1936; Undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
- Pariser Tageszeitung, 1936; Undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
- Pariser Tageszeitung, 1937; Undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
- Pariser Tageszeitung, 1938-1939; Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Pauli, Hertha, 1933-1935; 1939 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Pol, Therese, 1940; 1942; 1947-1949; 1953-1954; Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Prager Montagsblatt, 1933; Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Prager Montagsblatt, 1936; Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Prager Montagsblatt, 1937-1938; Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
- "The Queen of Villanueve", Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Révy, Richard and Alma Joe, 1942-1948; 1950-1951; 1959; 1961 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Riess, Curt, 1940; 1944; Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Rofts, Paul, 1963; Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Role of the Critic, 1922; 1924-1926; Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- "'Rote Fahnen' ueber Hollywood", Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Sachs, Nelly, 1946-1949 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Schwarzschild, Leopold, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Srill, Jacob, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Sternfeld, William, 1937; 1953 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Stössinger, Felix, 1935-1936 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Theaterkritiken A-Le (1 of 3), 1915-1933; Undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Theaterkritiken A-Le (2 of 3), 1915-1933; Undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Theaterkritiken A-Le (3 of 3), 1915-1933; Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Theaterkritiken Li-Z (1 of 3), 1915-1933; Undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Theaterkritiken Li-Z (2 of 3), 1915-1933; Undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Theaterkritiken Li-Z (3 of 3), 1915-1933; Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Tillinger, Eugene, 1933-1937; Undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
- "Tilsit 6. Juli", Undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Torberg, Friedrich, 1934; 1936; 1944-1945; 1950; Undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
- "Und Morgen Sind Wir in New York", Undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Untitled Manuscript, Undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Urzidil, Johannes, 1948; 1950; 1956 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Victor, Walther, 1933; 1936-1937; 1945 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Vierthel, Berthold, 1938-1939 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- von Jacoby, Lucy, 1945-1948; 1950; 1952; Undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
- "Walter Rathenau", Undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Weiskopf, Franz C., 1938 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Weltsch, Robert, 1939; 1966 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Wiener, Alfred, 1938-1939; 1955; Undated (Box 4, Folder 17)